<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Yassine Belmamoun - Personal Website - Tutorial</title><link href="https://www.yassinebelmamoun.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.yassinebelmamoun.com/feeds/tutorial.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.yassinebelmamoun.com/</id><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00+07:00</updated><subtitle>CTO @ Manatal.com &lt;br/&gt;Tech Entrepreneur &amp; Software Engineer</subtitle><entry><title>Blogging made simple</title><link href="https://www.yassinebelmamoun.com/start-your-blog-101.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-10-22T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2023-10-22T00:00:00+07:00</updated><author><name>Yassine Belmamoun</name></author><id>tag:www.yassinebelmamoun.com,2023-10-22:/start-your-blog-101.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every week, I invest a substantial amount of time reading, exploring podcasts and watching videos, all in the pursuit of knowledge. However, I've uncovered a missing piece in this quest: passive consumption of information isn't enough, there is immense value in creating content, exposing it to a wide audience to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every week, I invest a substantial amount of time reading, exploring podcasts and watching videos, all in the pursuit of knowledge. However, I've uncovered a missing piece in this quest: passive consumption of information isn't enough, there is immense value in creating content, exposing it to a wide audience to assist others and learn back from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's when I realized that I need to adjust the balance between the amount of content I passively consume and the amount of content that I actively produce. To get things rolling, I wanted to make things super easy for myself to publish articles on this blog. This post is all about sharing my current setup and explaining why and how I set it up this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choice of a solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the following requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed easy customization for my blog's format and design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The content I publish had to be reader-friendly, including support for code syntax highlighting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to steer clear of third-party dependencies like hosted platforms (Medium, Blogger, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing offline, even on a plane, had to be seamless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Budget-wise, I aimed for an economical approach, staying within the range of $20 per year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning a new technology was a no-go; simplicity was paramount.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Markdown had to be my go-to format for content creation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lastly, I wanted to avoid the complexities of handling intricate systems, like databases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I evaluated various solutions, which I categorized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managed Solutions (e.g. Medium, Blogger, Squarespace, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self Hosted Solutions&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Website Generator (e.g. Wordpress)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Static Website Generator (e.g. Jekyll, Hugo, Pelican)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managed solutions were quickly ruled out due to limitations like domain name usage restrictions, cost, and intrusive advertisements, among other issues. My focus shifted to self-hosted alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dismissed options like WordPress for being overly complex (e.g. databases), and honed in on lightweight solutions like static website generators—specifically Jekyll, Hugo, and Pelican.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I chose Pelican because it's built with Python, a language I'm comfortable with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a brief of how easy it is to set up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the Pelican library locally&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a command to quick start your project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Optional) Configure your project (e.g. themes, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write articles (and pages) in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a command to publish your articles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Producing content is straightforward: all you need is a text editor supporting Markdown. Then, you can track all changes with git history, publish your article with a simple &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; and host your entire blog on Github Pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This setup offers a portable self-hosted blog that's fully customizable. You can write offline, and the best part? It's entirely cost-free (e.g. the only cost would be for acquiring a domain name ~ 10$ per year).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you'd like to do the same, the only requirement is a very basic understanding of Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a more detailed tutorial on &lt;a href="https://www.yassinebelmamoun.com/pelican-tutorial.html"&gt;how to get started with Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tutorial"></category></entry></feed>